<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>applied machine learning on Pablo Hernandez Leal</title>
    <link>https://pablohl.github.io/tags/applied-machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in applied machine learning on Pablo Hernandez Leal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pablohl.github.io/tags/applied-machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From NeurIPS to the Real World: Key Takeaways from Competing in Pommerman</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/pommermanlessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/pommermanlessons/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;In theory there is no difference between theory and practice. In practice there is.&amp;rdquo; - Yogi Berra
  Back in 2018, the Pommerman Competition was announced to take place at NeurIPS. Together with Chao, Bilal, and Matt (my supervisor), we submitted an agent that secured 2nd place in the Learning Agents category. Reflecting on this experience —and trying to generalize about participating in competitions— I think there are lessons learned that are applicable in industry settings, such as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons From Six Years of Applied Machine Learning in Industry</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/industryvsacademia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/industryvsacademia/</guid>
      <description>It’s been more than six years since I started working in industry doing Machine Learning. I wanted to delve a bit deeper into my experience and what I have seen as differences between academic research (PhD) and applied research/data science. Below, I describe six lessons I have learned.
 1. I don’t have the time to do all the experiments I would like. When trying to get your research published, there are many experiments you need to perform.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
