<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pablo Hernandez Leal</title>
    <link>https://pablohl.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Pablo Hernandez Leal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pablohl.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Prompting, the Wonderful Wizard (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/prompts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/prompts/</guid>
      <description>This is my first post about Large Language Models (LLMs), and given all the information available, it&amp;rsquo;s challenging to write something novel that won&amp;rsquo;t become outdated soon. I wanted to start with something &amp;ldquo;reasonably&amp;rdquo; simple: prompting. In hindsight, I&amp;rsquo;ll conclude my post by arguing that prompting is not simple. It is both underestimated and overestimated in different aspects. In this first part of the post, my goal is to answer the following questions:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons From Six Years of Applied Machine Learning in Industry</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/industryvsacademia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/industryvsacademia/</guid>
      <description>It’s been more than six years since I started working in industry doing Machine Learning. I wanted to delve a bit deeper into my experience and what I have seen as differences between academic research (PhD) and applied research/data science. Below, I describe six lessons I have learned.
 1. I don’t have the time to do all the experiments I would like. When trying to get your research published, there are many experiments you need to perform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Research and Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/simplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/simplicity/</guid>
      <description>I think of myself as a Machine Learning (ML) person with my most recent application domain being finance. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve worked alongside &amp;ldquo;Quants&amp;rdquo;.
 According to ChatGPT: &amp;ldquo;In finance, a &amp;ldquo;quant&amp;rdquo; (short for quantitative analyst) is a professional who uses mathematical models, statistical techniques, and computer programming to analyze financial markets and securities. Quants develop algorithms and trading strategies to identify profitable opportunities and manage risk. They often work for investment banks, hedge funds, and other financial institutions, focusing on areas such as derivatives pricing, risk management, and algorithmic trading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on AI and Machine Learning for prospective/current students</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/thoughts/</guid>
      <description>This blog post was motivated when I was asked some interesting questions on AI and I thought it was good to share with a larger audience.
  Why did you choose AI? What excites you about it?
 I think my interest in machine learning (ML) started when I was doing my undergrad and I had to take some advanced courses. I think there were two courses &amp;ldquo;Artificial Intelligence&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Data mining&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a great supervisor (of an internship)?</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post I discussed how to be a great intern, now I&amp;rsquo;ll try to provide a complementary view on what I think a great supervisor should do.
 Trade-offs One of the most difficult parts of being a good supervisor is deciding what role you need to play during the internship to maximize both the intern&amp;rsquo;s interests and yours. For example, as a supervisor you can &amp;ldquo;force&amp;rdquo; the intern to work on your project/ideas, but if the intern is not interested it&amp;rsquo;s going to be a huge loss of time and effort (for both).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a great intern?</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</guid>
      <description>Tips and suggestions to make the most of an internship in tech. I’ve worked with many talented interns at throughtout my career and I wanted to share some general suggestions that might help you to improve your internship. Note: My experience is with research internships where the final outcome could be a paper submission.
 Expectations The first key aspect to understand are the expectations of your internship (both for you and your supervisor).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello world</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/hello_world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/hello_world/</guid>
      <description>I started my blog</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>About Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Pablo, I&amp;rsquo;m currently at Quantfury working on automated trading strategies. I have worked with proprietary data from retail activity. I have modelled and deployed a Reinforcement Learning agent for trading in live markets. Before joining Quantfury I spent some time at Borealis AI which is part of RBC (Royal Bank of Canada). I have worked on fundamental research, for example in multiagent deep reinforcement learning (for the NeurIPS Pommerman competition), auxiliary tasks for Deep RL and robustness in RL.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
