<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mentoring on Pablo Hernandez Leal</title>
    <link>https://pablohl.github.io/tags/mentoring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mentoring on Pablo Hernandez Leal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pablohl.github.io/tags/mentoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to be a great supervisor (of an internship)?</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post I discussed how to be a great intern, now I&amp;rsquo;ll try to provide a complementary view on what I think a great supervisor should do.
 Trade-offs One of the most difficult parts of being a good supervisor is deciding what role you need to play during the internship to maximize both the intern&amp;rsquo;s interests and yours. For example, as a supervisor you can &amp;ldquo;force&amp;rdquo; the intern to work on your project/ideas, but if the intern is not interested it&amp;rsquo;s going to be a huge loss of time and effort (for both).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a great intern?</title>
      <link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</guid>
      <description>Tips and suggestions to make the most of an internship in tech. I’ve worked with many talented interns at throughtout my career and I wanted to share some general suggestions that might help you to improve your internship. Note: My experience is with research internships where the final outcome could be a paper submission.
 Expectations The first key aspect to understand are the expectations of your internship (both for you and your supervisor).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
