<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Posts on Pablo Hernandez Leal</title>
		<link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Posts on Pablo Hernandez Leal</description>
		<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://pablohl.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
		<item>
			<title>How to be a great supervisor (of an internship)?</title>
			<link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_supervisor/</guid>
			<description>In my previous post I discussed how to be a great intern, now I&amp;rsquo;ll try to provide a complementary view on how I think a great supervisor should do.
 Trade-offs One of the most difficult parts of being a good supervisor is deciding what role you need to play during the internship to maximize both the intern&amp;rsquo;s interests and yours. For example, as a supervisor you can &amp;ldquo;force&amp;rdquo; the intern to work on your project/ideas, but if the intern is not interested it&amp;rsquo;s going to be a huge loss of time and effort (for both).</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous post I discussed <a href="https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/">how to be a great intern</a>, now I&rsquo;ll try to provide a complementary view on how I think a great supervisor should do.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="trade-offs">Trade-offs</h3>
<p>One of the most difficult parts of being a good supervisor is deciding what role you need to play during the internship <strong>to maximize both the intern&rsquo;s interests and yours</strong>. For example, as a supervisor you can &ldquo;force&rdquo; the intern to work on your project/ideas, but if the intern is not interested it&rsquo;s going to be a huge loss of time and effort (for both). The opposite is being a hands-off supervisor and giving minimal guidance to the intern. This might be a good learning experience for the intern to drive his own interests, however, the probability of completing something meaningful might be lower.
Another example of a trade-off happens when the intern &ldquo;is stuck&rdquo; (for example the intern is not sure why some experiments are giving incorrect results or the intern is not sure which experiment to try next). <strong>As a supervisor you probably have some ideas on how to solve the issue, however, you might choose not to do it right away</strong>. Why? I believe, as a supervisor <strong>you want to maximize both the outcome (and quality) of the internship project and the quality of the internship experience (i.e., how much the intern has learned).</strong> This translates into letting interns figure things out on their own in many cases. How much time to wait before actively helping the intern? That&rsquo;s the difficult part of being a good supervisor.</p>
<h3 id="focus">Focus</h3>
<p>You as a supervisor should know that <strong>internships are very short</strong>. So, try <strong>to be fully present</strong>. <strong>Do not think of other tasks you need to do. Do not casually check your email and slack. Devote the allocated time to focus on the internship project.</strong> What happens if there&rsquo;s no clear agenda on what to discuss? Then, you as a supervisor can ask more questions and lead the meeting. If there&rsquo;s nothing on the agenda that might be an indication that the intern might be stuck. Even if there&rsquo;s nothing else to discuss about the project (maybe you are waiting for some experiments to finish) I&rsquo;d say do not cancel the meeting or finish early. Use that allocated time to connect and try to build a relationship.</p>
<h3 id="motivation-and-support">Motivation and support</h3>
<p>One of the key characteristics of a good supervisor is <strong>being capable to motivate throughout the different stages of the internship</strong>. For example, at the beginning of the project a supervisor should be capable of describing some interesting problems that deserve to be studied. If the supervisor is not able to convince an intern that a problem is interesting then the intern might not want to work on that!  In contrast, at the end of the internship a supervisor should be able to describe the contribution and how the project improved previous works. This is important because when you (the intern) are close to finishing the internship you will see your work as minimal, &ldquo;not so great&rdquo; or &ldquo;just ok&rdquo;. However, probably this happens because you worked on that for some time that <em>seems</em> easy. It&rsquo;s your supervisor&rsquo;s job to convince you of the good work that you have done. Lastly, a supervisor can actively help the intern with a recommendation for a full time job. In summary, a good supervisor should support the intern at all times during the internship (and sometimes beyond that period).</p>
<h3 id="documentation-and-feedback">Documentation and feedback</h3>
<p>My Ph.D. supervisor said something like <strong>&ldquo;the better the quality of the document the better the quality of the feedback&rdquo;</strong>. What this means is that when you share a document/report that is not close to the final version (for example with some incoherent ideas, lack of structure, unclear sentences, etc) then it&rsquo;s very hard to give detailed feedback. The best one can provide is high-level comments like &ldquo;this paragraph is not clear&rdquo;, &ldquo;move this content to that section&rdquo;, &ldquo;organize the experiments in this way&rdquo;, etc. Once the document becomes easier to read and has sufficient structure then the feedback will change and it will be the point when the supervisor will make more &ldquo;interesting&rdquo; comments.</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>I mentioned <em>a few</em> examples of what I consider makes a good supervisor. They come in different forms and people have different strengths. This means that an amazing researcher does not always equal an amazing supervisor. An amazing engineer does not always mean an amazing supervisor. I think co-supervision might be a good tactic to get better feedback as an intern and to improve/grow as a supervisor.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>How to be a great intern?</title>
			<link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/great_intern/</guid>
			<description>Tips and suggestions to make the most of an internship in tech. I’ve worked with many talented interns at throughtout my career and I wanted to share some general suggestions that might help you to improve your internship. Note: My experience is with research internships where the final outcome could be a paper submission.
 Expectations The first key aspect to understand are the expectations of your internship (both for you and your supervisor).</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="tips-and-suggestions-to-make-the-most-of-an-internship-in-tech">Tips and suggestions to make the most of an internship in tech.</h1>
<p>I’ve worked with many talented interns at throughtout my career and I wanted to share some general suggestions that might help you to improve your internship. Note: My experience is with <em>research</em> internships where the final outcome could be a paper submission.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="expectations">Expectations</h3>
<p>The first key aspect to understand are the <em>expectations of your internship (both for you and your supervisor)</em>. An internship <em>is not like a mini Ph.D</em>. and <em>it is not like a final project</em> in a CS course.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve seen internships where the supervisor has clearly delineated a project with a problem and possible solutions, then your work it&rsquo;s probably going to be following your supervisor&rsquo;s ideas. On the other hand, it could be a very open-ended internship where you are given the freedom to work on whatever you like. <em>Which one is better? Depends on you and your goals</em>. If you get an internship after 3 years on Ph.D. you probably have a good idea of how to do research and areas of interest. However, for a more junior intern, having more concrete steps and ideas would be more beneficial.</p>
<p>My suggestion is to understand the expectations of your internship and talk with your supervisor on what style/approach you are going to use on the project. Setting clear expectations from the beginning could help you to plan and have a better experience in your internship.</p>
<h3 id="duration">Duration</h3>
<p>A second highly important aspect that you need to understand is that <strong>internships are very short</strong>, 4-6 months are usually not enough to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Understand a new topic/problem</li>
<li>Propose a solution</li>
<li>Implement it</li>
<li>Run experiments</li>
<li>Write a paper</li>
</ol>
<p>Usually, <em>your supervisor</em> needs to drive and define the first two tasks (your supervisor will also help you with the paper). In contrast, <em>you will be the main driver</em> of the implementation and experimental evaluation (this means that your supervisor won&rsquo;t be checking your code).</p>
<h3 id="documentation">Documentation</h3>
<p>Another key element to understand is that supervisors usually have other projects as their main responsibility and doing <em>context switching is tiring and difficult</em>. You as an intern can help your supervisor by <strong>keeping a structured documentation</strong> of the research/experiments/ideas that you have performed (I’ve seen people use Google docs and markdown editors, like hackMD.io). You don’t want to spend too much time on the document but it needs to have a logical structure that makes it easier to find something. A simple approach is to sort chronologically (most recent ideas/experiments at the beginning), this would also be helpful later if you need to write a report of your internship.</p>
<h3 id="communication">Communication</h3>
<p>Documentation will be a starting point to have conversations and hopefully fruitful discussions. But, for this to happen you&rsquo;ll need to develop <strong>good communication with your supervisor and/or peers</strong>. Unfortunately, this will not happen on the first day. You haven&rsquo;t worked together and you don&rsquo;t know how to communicate efficiently, probably it will take some time for you to adjust and improve that. My suggestion is to build a relationship with your peers/supervisors. How to do it? well&hellip;  try to not always talk about your project or work, spend some time chitchatting. I believe it should really be the supervisor&rsquo;s work to make the effort and build a relationship but supervisors are far from perfect and they might not know how to do it, so, you can try leading this part.</p>
<h3 id="quality-of-feedback">Quality of Feedback</h3>
<p>A last suggestion is trying to <strong>maximize the quality of the feedback you get in your meetings</strong>. As I mentioned, your supervisor might not be checking every day on you, so use your time efficiently. If you have followed the suggestion above about keeping good documentation, <em>you can share it with your supervisor before the meeting</em>, they can take a look if they have time and they will already have a context to start with during the meeting. You can also be prepared for the meeting with a list of questions/ideas/experiments that you want to discuss further.</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>In my opinion internships have a lot of <em>randomness</em> involved and usually are a hit or miss situation. I think that if you applied and got an internship position you will have amazing expectations of proposing a new algorithm, submitting a new a paper and possibly getting an offer of a job after the internship&hellip; that’s a good attitude, but you also need to accept that <em><strong>internships sometimes don’t work out and that is also fine</strong></em>. I usually tell interns that the goal that I have for the internship is that:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>They should have learned something new</strong>: in a technical way, for example by reading and discussing a couple of papers, and at least implementing/testing one in more depth.</li>
<li><strong>They should have improved a few <em>soft skills</em></strong>: at the end of the internship you should have given a couple of presentations, prepared a report (or paper) and you had to interact and exchange ideas with other peers. These skills are valuable no matter which company or job, so practice and keep improving.</li>
</ul>
<p>If we also get a paper submission that’s extra.</p>
<p>A last piece of advice is that internships are a good way to get a tiny look into a company but don’t be fooled to think that you will understand every aspect of it. Enjoy your internship and try to learn as much as possible.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Hello world</title>
			<link>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/hello_world/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://pablohl.github.io/posts/hello_world/</guid>
			<description>I started my blog</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started my blog</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
